Guide to the French Revolution and Napoleonic Period Manuscripts, 1752-1882 (bulk 1788-1815)
French Revolution and Napoleonic Period Manuscripts, 1752-1882 (bulk 1788-1815)
- Autograph manuscripts
  - S (Box 13)
    - Sébastiani, Minister of Foreign Affairs, 1. Aug. 1832; 1 leaf (Box 13, Folder 11)
      ALS in French: passport for the Count of Alton-Shée
    - Ségur, Louis Philippe de, to Bigot de Préameneu, 24 Aug. 1807; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Ségur, Louis Philippe de, to M. de Sireuil, 19 Apr. 1782; 1 leaf (Box 13, Folder 12b)
      ALS in French: informing Sireuil that the King has approved giving him the pension earned by his brother, who fought for the American side in the Revolutionary War
    - Semonville, Charles Louis Huguet de, to M. Berger, 27 July 1814; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Senaux, Jean Pierre de, to the Prince de Lamballe, 24 Nov. 1766; 1 leaf (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Serrurier, Marshall, 1812; 1 leaf (Box 13, Folder 15)
      ALS in French: comptability
    - Servan de Gerbey, Joseph, 25 April 1799; 1 leaf (Box 13, Folder 16)
      ALS in French: statement of readiness for military service.
    - Servan de Gerbey, Joseph, to M. Villemanzy, 4 June 1806; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - Sicard, Abbé Roche Ambroise, to M. Barbier, Librarian, 19 Sept. 1808; 1 leaf+ 5 leaves (Box 13, Folder 19)
      ALS in French, on his school for the deaf, plus bibliographical notes and portraits.
    - Sieyès, Emmanuel Joseph, to M. sabatier, 24 Jan. 1799; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 13, Folder 20)
      ALS in French, plus translation, plus bibliographical notes
    - Sieyès, Emmanuel Joseph, to Laharpe, Membre du Directoire Helvétique, 19 June 1799; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 7 leaves (Box 13, Folder 21)
      ALS in French, plus a certificate of authenticity, plus bibliographical notes and portraits of both Laharpe and Sieyès
    - Sieyès, Emmanuel Joseph, to Bertin, Ordonnateur de la Marine, 28 Aug. 1799; 2 leaves + 1 leaf (Box 13, Folder 22)
    - Sijas, Prosper, to the Adminsitrators of Paris, 8 oct. 1793; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 13, Folder 23)
      ALS in French, letterhead illustrated with a a red liberty cap, plus translation
    - Société populaire de Mâcon, 1793; 1 leaf (Box 13, Folder 24)
      ALS in French: certificate of membership of Citizen Roberjot, with interesting printed vignette
    - Sombreuil., Marquis de, to the Minister of War, 13 Aug. 1788; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 13, Folder 25)
    - Soult, Nicolas, to Barbier, [Tarente] 31 Oct. 1801; 1 leaf + 12 leaves (Box 13, Folder 26)
    - Staël-Holstein, Anne Louise Germaine de, to MM. Le Roy, Bayard and McEvers [bankers in New York], [Stockholm] 25 March 1813; 1 leaf (Box 13, Folder 27)
      ALS in French [duplicata], regarding investments issues; the intrigues between General Moreau, then banished in New York, and General Bernadotte, now crown prince of Sweden and at the head of an army opposing Napoleon; and on the prospect of having her son Albert appointed diplomat to the USA (he would be killed in a duel in July 1813.)
    - Staël-Holstein, Anne Louise Germaine de, to M. de Montlosier, n.d.; 1 leaf (Box 13, Folder 28)
      ALS in Frenc: invitation to supper
    - Strub, Colonel Xavier, 4 July 1814; 1 leaf (Box 13, Folder 29)
      ALS in French: resume
    - Suchet, Marshall, to the Treasurer of the Legion of Honor, 17 Sept. 1814; 1 leaf + 12 leaves (Box 13, Folder 30)
    - Suffren, Bailli de, August 1774; 1 leaf (Box 13, Folder 31)
      ALS in French: report dealing with the events of a tour of duty at sea
    - Suisse. Stapfer [Minister to France] to, 28 Dec. 1800; 1 leaf (Box 13, Folder 32)
      ALS in French: certificate for Citizen Bernard, with printed vignette of the Légation Helvétique à Paris.
  - T-Z (Box 14)
    - Taillade, Colonel, to Commodore Porter, 11 Jan. 1818; 1 leaf + 6 leaves (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Talleyrand-Périgord, Charles Maurice de, Foreign Minister to all French civil and military officers, 16 december 1798; 1 leaf (Box 14, Folder 2a)
      ALS in French: passport and laissez-passer for Citizen Mangourit, the French agent in Saint-Maurice-en-Vallais, Switzerland, also certifying that his name never appeared on any "liste d'émigrés"
    - Talleyrand-Périgord, Charles Maurice de, to the Minister of Finance, 1803; 1 leaf (Box 14, Folder 2b)
    - Talleyrand-Périgord, Charles Maurice de, to the Minister of Interior*, 9 February 1804; 1 leaf (Box 14, Folder 2c)
      ALS in French, recommending Louis Bignon for the position of sous-préfet of Sisteron, "dont il a été absent pendant toute la durée des fonctions qu'il a remplies au Levant. Cette longue absence l'ayant rendu étranger à tous les partis qui ont divisé les esprits pendant le cours de la Révolution, il serait par cela seul plus propre que tout autre à l'exercice de [la] place qu'il sollicite; il pourrait d'ailleurs par quelques ressources personnelles suppléer à la modicité du traitement affecté à la sous-préfecture."
    - Tallien, Jean Lambert, to Réal, n.d. [1795?]; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 14, Folder 3)
      ALS in French:, plus translation
    - Tallien, Jean Lambert, to the Administrators of the National Domains of Egypt, [Cairo, Egypt] 12 aug. 1797; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Tallien, Jeanne Marie Cabarrus, Princess of Chimay, to a General, 17 Dec. 1817; 1 leaf + 6 leaves (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Talma, to Mme Caroline Talma born Vanhove, n.d. [c. 1820]; 1 leaf + 4 leaves (Box 14, Folder 6)
      ALS in French, plus translation and notes: on domestic issues, with mentions of several children of the actor. either from different beds, or adopted
    - Tilly, General, to the Minister of War, 1798; 1 leaf (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Tilly, General, to the Director of Posts, 11 Dec. 1799; 1 leaf (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Tilly, General, to the Director of Posts in Belgium, 13 Dec. 1799; 1 leaf (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Tollenarre, to ?, 24 oct. 1796; 1 leaf (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Tourzel, Louise Elisabeth, Duchesse de, to [Marquis de Dreux-Brézé?], n.d. [after 1815]; 1 leaf + 6 leaves (Box 14, Folder 11a)
      ALS in French: intercession in favor of Mme de Kleist, who was attached to the children of late King Louis XVI.
    - Treilhard, Jean-Baptiste, May 1796; 1 leaf (Box 14, Folder 11b)
      ALS in French re: la publication de la liste des citoyens composant le jury d'accusation et de jugement (au tribunal criminel de Paris) pour les mois de juin, juillet et aout 1796.
    - Truguet, to the Minister of Finance, 11 April 1796; 1 leaf (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Truguet, to the Minister of Finance, 24 Febr. 1797; 1 leaf (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Vallée, Comte Sylvain Charles, 4 Jan. 1834; 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Vallier, Augustin, 1793; 1 leaf (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Vernier, to Citizen Gaudin, Minister of Finance, 31 March 1803; 1 leaf (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - Versailles, Comité de Surveillance, 10 May 1794; 1 leaf (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - Versailles, Comité de Surveillance, 23 July 1794; 1 leaf (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Victor, General [Captain General of Louisiana], to the General Commandant of the French Troops Stationed at Batavia., [Paris] 6 Nov. 1804; 1 leaf + 5 leaves (Box 14, Folder 19)
      ALS in French: military orders, plus portraits
    - Vigée-Lebrun, Mme, 20 June 1832; 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Vignolle, General Martin, to Delorme, [Ragusa] 14 Aug. 1806; 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Vignon, Barthelemy, to the Treasurer of Holland, 1809; 1 leaf (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - Villaret de Joyeuse, to Joseph-Alphonse Esménard, [Martinique] 11 Jan. 1818; 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 14, Folder 17)
      ALS in French, plus partial translation, portrait and notes
    - Villeret, Brun de, to M. Tardieu, 1 leaf (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Villetard, Alexandre, to the Minister of Finance, 1801; 1 leaf (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - Villetard, Alexandre, to to the Minister of Finance, 7 Jan. 1803; 1 leaf (Box 14, Folder 20)
    - Villetard, Alexandre, to the Minister of Finance, 15 Jan. 1803; 1 leaf (Box 14, Folder 21)
    - Volney de Chasseboeuf, Constantin, to ?, 1801; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 14, Folder 22)
      ALS in French, plus t ranslation and portrait
    - Willot, Victor-A., to ?, 7 Sept. 1802; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 14, Folder 23)
- Bound Manuscripts
  - Journal Manuscrit of Claude-Charles Coster, vol.1, 19 April - 29 December 1790; Bound Ms. 1 Item 1; 1 bound manuscript
    Autograph manuscript in French. "Coster le jeune" was born in Nancy in 1741. He pursued a distinguished administrative career, especially under Necker. In 1790-91 he was chef de bureau at the Constituant Assembly, where both his brother Sigisbert, a chanoine de la cathédrale de Verdun, and his brother-in-law, Pierre-Joseph Prugnon, were deputies [a copy of the former's own journal is in the Archives nationales in Paris, C 26 dossier 13]. He kept this political diary in part to keep informed his protector, Marshall Prince of Beauvau-Craon, who was living in his château du Val in Saint-Germain-en-Laye most of the time. His information generally comes straight out of the minutes of the Assembly's meetings. A moderate royalist, Coster mentions the reactions of the public, which he calls "l'excécrable populace de Paris" or "les enragés"; he also reports different events and rumors of plots, arrestations, assassinations, and emigrations, that were the talk of the Assembly.
  - Journal Manuscrit of Claude-Charles Coster, vol.2, 1781-1792 [Bulk 14 March - 18 July 1791]; Bound Ms. 1 Item 2; 1 bound manuscript
    Follow-up of the journal, plus transcription of revolutionary songs, plus letters sent to Coster between 1781 and December 1792.
  - Set of 102 documents, with pages numbered 1-311, 1790-1815; Bound Ms. 3 ++; 1 bound manuscript
    Contains, e.g., "un rolle des officiers mariniers, matelots et mousses employés au Lac de Garde", 1796; a report from "Ernoulf, capitaine général de la Guadeloupe et dépendances, au Citoyen Portalis, chargé de toutes les affaires concernant les cultes", 1804; a letter by printer Firmin-Didot to the minister of Finance, about the production of official seals and stamps, 1805; another form the bishop of Mayence calling for the conversion of the Bitche citadel into a church, 1805; and one from the Bordeaux Chamber of Commerce to the Minister of Finance protesting the high taxation of beverages, 1814.
  - "Registre des délibérations prises par le Comité de surveillance établi au fort de La Malgue [Toulon] le 26 août 1793"., 26 August 1793; Bound Ms. 4 ++; 1 bound manuscipt
    Contains a list of the twelve members of this royalist committee as well as a list of the prisoners kept in the fort.
  - "Réclamation des courtisanes parisiennes adressée à l'Assemblée nationale concernant l'abolition des titres déshonorants tels que garces, putains, toupies, maquerelles, etc, etc.", [1790] mid 19th century; Bound Ms. 7; 4 leaves
    Manuscript copy of a revolutionary pamphleet. A note indicates that the copyist was the famous Parisian bibliographer Jacques Charles Brunet (1780-1867.)
  - Minutes of the correspondence sent by the "Comité général des sections de Toulon", 19 July-4 October 1793; Bound Ms. 7 ++; 1 bound manuscript
  - "Registre des arrêtés et réquisitions pris par les représentants du peuple [près les armées et départements du Midi] Paul Barras et Fréron commencé le 21 brumaire an II de la République [et se terminant le 20 pluviôse].", Nov. 1793-Febr. 1794; Bound Ms. 8 ++; 1 bound manuscipt, 68 p.
    Documents the revolt of Toulon and the Jacobine repression.
  - ALS from Napoléon Bonaparte to Major General Berthier, 8 April 1809; Bound Ms. 9; 1 letter
    Strategic instructions for the early stages of the campaign in Germany which culminated in the French victory of Wagram. The letter has been published in the "Correspondance de Napoléon Ier", 1865, vol. 18, nr. 15030.
  - Miscellaneae, 1779-1790; Bound Ms. 10; 1 little box containing 2 letters and 6 graphics, numbered 4606 Bd. Ms. 10 /1-8
    Includes a letter from Necker to Beaumarchais on the arms-for-tobacco deal with America, 1779 (10-1), another from Calonne to Beaumarchais about a favor made by court banker Micault d'Harvelay, n.d. (10-2), a portrait of Mme Necker (10-3), an allegory of "Time", n.d. (10-4), a caricature of Lafayette, Bailly and d'Orléans as "animaux malfaisants", c. 1790 (10-5), another of Philippe d'Orléans as King of Spades or "Philippe pique", c. 1790 (10-6), another of Lafayette, October 1789 (10-7), and a royalist engraving blasting "[les] brigands furieux [qui] ont mis la france au pillage", n.d. (10-8.)
  - "Souvenirs, anecdotes et pensées diverses, ou Morale de l'histoire et des philosophes", late 18th century; Bound Ms. 11; 1 bound manuscript
    Anonymous volume of "souvenirs" and historical notations, most about ancient Rome, confirming that "the French Revolution was played in Roman clothes" (Karl Marx).
  - "Lettres de cachet", 1755-1791; Bound Ms. 12++; 1 bound manuscript
    Contains 141 original documents assembled by A.D. White, mostly related to the judicial system of Old Regime France: lettres de cachet (i.e., letters signed by the king of France [in this case, Louis XVI], countersigned by one of his ministers, and closed with the royal seal, or cachet [here, 4 letters still bear it]. They contained orders directly from the king, often to enforce arbitrary actions and judgements that could not be appealed; passports and special authorizations to sojourn in Paris (e.g., for Alsatian Jews); also, an order to accommodate the arrival of the future Queen Marie-Antoinette in France in February 1770.